Great to be back.
I'm sure you're eager.
There's no way the first question is
about Nick, is it?
Um,
yeah. Gave us a just rolled his ankle
yesterday and uh he's got a low low
ankle sprain. Um going to do the
walkthrough today. We're not sure if how
extensive if at all he's going to
practice. Um but he's confident, got a
great plan. Uh fully expect him to play.
So, um, good, you know, right where we
want to be. So, uh, but he's doing great
and moving around. Just got to, uh, make
sure we handle it and handle it the
right way and probably going to be over
over careful and, um, over cautious at
this point to, uh, make sure we're
rolling going into the weekend.
>> Hey, coach, over here on the left, um,
you know, you talk about playing a style
that nobody wants to match. Um, how does
that figure into your your practice
philosophy in terms of padded practices
and and getting ready for a game like
this?
>> We we uh we
we practice the amount of reps and
intensity on what we feel like what we
need to do to go play our best football.
So, um sometimes it's putting pads on to
make sure our pad level is up to up to
snuff and our physicality is is ready to
go. And uh sometimes we don't. Sometimes
we some we call it ACT practice.
Sometimes we're in ACT tempo. We're
changing tempos all the time. Uh Sam
Ramsey does a great job uh of uh of
helping us on a daily basis of what the
guys outputs are and what they can
handle and when we can push and when we
can't. So um I don't know. I feel like
our I feel like our uh injury history
over the last two years is is uh just as
good as anybody else in the league. So
you can you can test me on that one, but
I'm pretty sure we're up there.
>> Hey, coach over here
>> Mark Fucle. How are you?
>> Hey, good to see um you pulled me aside
after opening night and said you'd wish
you'd answered my question a little bit
differently. Uh that question was to get
to this point you had to sacrifice a lot
and what do you feel was the biggest
thing that you had to sacrifice to get
here?
Well, um, you know, actually reflecting
on it, it's not really me that's sacrif
I mean it's I mean the easy the the
layup answer is time. Uh, but to me it's
your what are your loved ones willing to
willing to sacrifice. I mean there's
there's some things that you inevitably
have to miss uh what you don't want to
but uh you know I think of what my wife
has has has sacrificed up to this point.
you know, a couple years ago we were
playing the AFC Championship game and
two days later I we flew to Seattle and
we stayed there, you know, all the way
across the country and uh in the moment
you know it was a it was it felt like
that was a big you know obviously a huge
decision but man we're really blessed
and happy that that happened and um you
know it's funny how those things have a
have a way of uh of shaking out that way
but you have to have faith in the
process and and uh took a lot of faith
on her part so I think it's probably
your loved ones around you
>> Mike right
um when you got here and you and John
were sort of assessing the roster, just
how how are those conversations in terms
of here's how we're going to build it
out, the moves we need to make, and then
maybe how's it kind of played out
relative to what you thought it would?
>> Well, I think uh I think I think that
was also a process with pretty much
everything else we've done in our
program since we got here. Um I really
enjoyed, you know, understanding what
our people thought of our players. a lot
of our players, you know, we've talked
about throughout the season, you know,
the Drake Thomas is a world, the
Taiakata is a world that I wasn't very
familiar with coming in. Uh I think it
was a balance of like, hey, these are
the physical traits or things that we
want our our players to be able to do at
these given positions. But I, you know,
I don't think that we're like rigid and
saying like this guy has to be like
this, go find me a Nick Aman worry, he's
got to be 63, he's got to run a 4-3.
It's like there's only so many of those
people walking the planet, you know? Uh
but it's it's also mentality. It's um
you know, communication, all those
different types of things. It's their
love for football, I think, which was a
easy which was something that we shared
from the get-go, the toughness factor,
the grit factor, those types of things.
Um we're definitely aligned from the
get-go.
>> Hey, coach, uh right here, uh your team
excels at tackling, uh just at a high
level, your team tackles and especially
effectively. What was the process like
getting your team to that level tackling
and why is it so important to uh
effectively tackle and defensive side of
the ball? Well, I have to give just
about all the credit to Chris Partridge.
Uh, you know, when he when we were at
Michigan after I left, um, and I don't
want to quote coach Harbaugh here
because I wasn't there, but basically
created like a finish coach and, uh, CP
was there for that. And he had an idea
of of kind of building out a curriculum
for us on how we want to finish plays.
And we ended up calling it eat, effort,
effort, angle, and tackling. And, and CP
has spearheaded that that project from
the day one. The guys love it and it's
something we drill the the fundamental
of of tackling and finishing every day.
We do it as a team. We do it in our
warm-up before games. Uh it's it's just
kind of part of our DNA and the guys
take a lot of pride in it and when it
when it hits, you know, it's the way
that you want it, it's powerful stuff
and and when you don't hit it, it's it
can get ugly. So the guys understand the
importance of it and uh we take a lot of
pride in it.
Hi, coach. Just one more about Nick.
It's not about the injury, but you've
seen a lot of football players. How do
you react to a rookie player who's able
to learn fast and fly all around the
field like that? And is it even
surprising for some of the players on
the team?
>> Well, I think I think this is a a great
example of can we have buyin really when
you look, if you draft a player, it's
great to have alignment behind it
because you know that you're going to be
investing like full tilt into their
development. what they have. Nick's kind
of a a special example of that, but it's
still, you know, kind of apples to
apples is [snorts] even if you were to
pick like a, you know, fifth or sixth
rounder. Uh, but I think it was all
hands on deck. The coaches having a
vision for we wanted to create Nick
being bought in and committed to doing
those like daily steps and then, you
know, our veterans on our team. Um, you
know, it's easy it's easy for vets to be
like, "Hey, you drafted this guy. Okay,
is he here to replace me? What's the
deal?" You know, okay, do we really want
the you know, how much do we help the
guy? I think the beauty behind our team
is like our vets have embraced our
rookies. Our rookies have had a lot of
respect for our veterans from the day
they walked in the door and it's meshed
really well where each each each side
can really push each other and um and I
think that's I think that's how you get
to where we are today with Nick. So um
it's a great example how about how we
want to operate.
>> Hey Mike, um you've talked about
connection on this team and just now you
talked about veterans and the young
players connection. I'm wondering if you
could talk about your assistant coach's
connection to the players in that how
that's that spread out and built up for
your defense and offense.
>> Yeah, thanks for bringing that up. It's
uh you know
again I've never had our staff before
but as you you know before last year but
as you're visualizing hey what's
important to us how we want to operate
as as a coaching staff as a football
team you know
if if you and I aren't connected and I'm
coaching you there's no way in heck
you're going to ever do anything that
I'm asking you to do. So it's kind of
like that's the that's the starting
point of who we want to coach our
football team and be be around our
players every day. and our guys have
just done a phenomenal job. And I look,
I mean, football, like football teams
are like the coolest thing ever. You got
people from all these different
backgrounds, all these different
experiences, all these different
expertises, and somehow you can kind of
come together in a way where we're all
kind of helping each other and going in
the same direction. I think that's a
powerful thing. And um our coaches are
living, breathing examples of that every
day. They do a phenomenal job.
Hey Mike, following that up over here on
your right, regarding Jay Harbaugh, your
special teams coordinator, what stood
out in your time around him [snorts]
before hiring him for your staff and and
how has his characteristics or how have
his characteristics kind of enabled that
unit to be such a complimentary force?
>> I love bragging on Jay because um he's a
uh he's kind of like a underrated hero
behind this whole operation. J J J J J J
J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J I met Jay
when I became an intern. He he's the one
who interviewed me in Baltimore back in
14 and um that's kind of that's where
our friendship started and he was a QC
on offense actually working for Gary
Kubak at the time which is a small world
but um and then he left to coach with
his dad at Michigan and we stayed in
touch but when I got to Michigan became
very clear very very quickly that this
guy was a heck of a football coach. Uh
great eye for talent. the way he got buy
in and the way that he like creatively
coached these awesome fundamentals and
the guys like love the process in
special teams in college like that
doesn't mean Michigan's a special place
that doesn't happen all the time all
across the country it wasn't my
experience at Georgia and uh I was like
man this is awesome this is really rad
and this guy's a really dang good coach
and then he coached running backs he
coached tight ends I left he became the
safeties coach this guy can coach
football and uh you think about his how
he operates and what his mentality
thought he is. I mean, it was like a
very very easy decision to be to beg him
to come to Seattle and be our special
teams coordinator and um and he's done a
tremendous job since day one. Talking
about chasing edges, this guy, that's
how he operates all the time. Pushing
the envelope, he pushes me. He's got a
great perspective. Um not afraid to
challenge the status quo. I mean, all
those things. Just the list goes on and
on. Jay's Jay's Jay's awesome.
>> Coach, back here on your right, um it's
been a long week. I'm sure you've
answered more questions than you could
have imagined. Um, but the bond has
really come through talking to the
players over the last three days. Is is
there a moment over the last three or
four days that has stood out to you that
sort of says, "We're here. We're ready."
Just something behind the scenes that
has leapt out to you?
>> Well, you know, we do what we do and on
every third Thursday, we do a walk-in
talk and we did it today and um
hopefully the guys don't mind me. But
the last question was like, "Hey, 10
years from now when we have a team
reunion, like what are you guys going to
remember, you know, and uh about this
team?" And um I think shadow boxing was
probably the most popular answer, but uh
just just for those guys who share those
laughs and the and the funny stories,
all the things that you you know, you
probably haven't heard that are kind of
behind the scenes, just the list goes on
and on. It's just it's a great it's a
special group.
>> Hey, Mike. Um over here, uh
congratulations on on a great season.
What what did um uh you know, you've
been on the coaching grind for a long
time. What would your advice be to young
assistants, you got a lot of them who
want to be where you are. They want to
be OC's, eventually head coaches. Your
advice to them and then uh to there are
a lot of young black assistants. You
know, this year there were no black head
coaches hiring the cycle, but your
advice to them in terms of just keeping
keeping optimistic, uh keeping on the
grind. just sort of your advice and
perspective.
>> Well, my advice to those folks would be
the same advice as to anybody else. Um,
I think the first thing you have to
realize is everybody's timeline is
different. And if you do a great job,
like one of my fears is like that you're
a fraud. Like if you just don't know,
you know, like it's it's tough to be in
a situation where you just feel like
you're stuck and you don't know. So,
make sure you're doing the work on the
front end to build a solid foundation so
when you do get your opportunities,
you're ready to go. Um, from my
experience when I've had an attitude of
like, oh, I got to get to the next thing
and I got to be a position coach or I
need to be a coordinator. It's like
doesn't work like that. You know, those
opportunities didn't come. You know, I
was very humbled very quickly. But when
I've had the opportunity when I've had
the attitude of, man, let me just be the
best QC that George has ever had. you
know, let me be the guy that is the is
the is the the point man on how the
meals work, where the coffee is made,
how do you do the playbook, you know,
like when I took that mentality on,
that's where I felt like I gained trust
and and more responsibilities and um
they call it the just can you can you
help your team succeed and add value,
especially the person that you're
working for. Can you set them up for
success? Um, I've been very fortunate
and blessed that these opportunities
have happened uh relatively quickly, but
um and so I I can imagine that some
people get frustrated when you know
their time hasn't felt like they haven't
come yet. But I promise you this this is
a competitive enough uh profession and
and game and and popular enough where
and it's efficient enough where we'll
find the best people and word travels
quickly and you can't it's it's you're
hard to you're hard to hide. So, um,
trust the process and and, uh, and your
time will come, but make sure you're
ready.
>> Excuse me. Um, Mike, um, the practice
squad guys, Mike, right? Right.
>> Sorry, Bo.
>> Um, the practice squad, the ready squad
guys as you guys have named him. Um, the
obvious importance is that they get
elevated on game day, but how important
are they to what you guys do kind of
during the week and and all of that? And
then how cool is it that those guys get
to have this experience as well?
Well, I I think I think the the
fundamental answer to that, Bob, is like
we call them the ready squad, but they
are they're part of the 70, you know, so
they they're on our they're they're part
of our team. They're an integral part of
our operation. Uh it's kind of a dual
purpose during the season is is to make
sure we're we're preparing, you know,
your respective side of the ball as well
as you possibly can, but it's also
developmental aspect as well, too. like
we should be stacking great reps
throughout the week and you're you
should be getting and you're getting
coached up on those as well. So, um
that's our philosophy and you know,
you've seen our history throughout the
season. I mean, we're elevating guys
every week when they're ready to go and
guys have done a great job when they've
elevated and really help us win, you
know, several of these games because
they they've they've we treat them and
they expect to um you know, like like
they're a normal player part of the
team. So, um, and in fact, like that
that you're happy for them that they
have this operate that this, uh, this
experience, it's kind of like I'm you're
happy as as, uh, the rest of the roster,
you know, the rest of the people in the
organization. So, um, they've done
they've done a great job. We got we got
a really deep, young, talented roster
and, um, they deserve to be here.
>> Coach Myra Gomez International Media,
congratulations and best of luck this
Sunday. Two things. Um the first one a
couple of the players have talked about
having some of the players from Legend
of Boom you know times come in and talk
to them. So if you can just talk to a
little bit about how important that
mentorship has been overall for your
defense. And then the second thing is on
diversification. You talked a little bit
about having people from different
backgrounds, different places of life
and this is the first Super Bowl where
we have a lot of Latinos being a part of
it. But you have Latinos, you have
white, you have black, you have whatever
identification come all coming together
for the love of the sport. And of course
in your team personally trying to
compete for this Lombardi.
>> What was the first question?
>> The first question was the importance of
mentorship.
>> Oh, mentorship.
>> Yeah. Look, I think uh I think we came
in with the mentality of hey like this
is a this is an awesome organization
with a really cool history especially on
defense. uh a lot of the players still
have, you know, spend a lot of time in
Seattle, so we wanted to take advantage
of the opportunity to have those people
around. Uh, you know, I think assurm
coming to talk to our team this off
seasonason about playing at home,
playing at Lumen and making that place
come alive and I think that really
resonated with our players, uh, there's
so many other more examples and and and
they know this, but officially like on
the record, I mean, they're always I
mean, doors are open all the time to
these guys and um, they're around all
the time. It's it's a blast. I mean,
look at you grew up, you're a fan of
these people growing up, especially me.
So, to have them, you know, want to be a
play a role in our football team is um
is pretty awesome in terms of
diversification or, you know, whatever
word you want to call it. It's just
we're we're in the business of team
building, you know, and trying to be the
best team we can possibly be. And
turns out that's what makes the best
teams. So, it's pretty simple pretty
simple decision criteria on our part,
frankly. So, um, and we love it, you
know, it's just, but the common thread
is we love football. You know, we love
the process and, uh, and when you do
that, you know, you can you can come up
with something pretty special.
>> Two more.
>> Hey, Mike on your left. Um, both you
guys and the Patriots run a lot of
stunts, games, and you're good at it.
Uh, how big of a of a factor do you
think that's going to be on Sunday, the
ability to for one of the teams to
really defend it well? And also, what's
the key to being a good stunting team?
Well, uh, with the with the first
question, it's going to be it's going to
be a a pretty big driving force behind
how you affect the quarterback this
game. Uh, it does allow you to rush less
people and try to create pressure as
well. So, that's one of the reasons that
we do it. And I think in order to be
effective about it, you can't be robots.
You know, there's a lot of like uh
chemistry that has to happen for you.
There's the the timing of the stunts and
like angles and things like that are
really just kind of like chiseled away
at over the course of time where you
understand like how guys run different
stunts and the timing of it and then
versus different protection schemes as
well. How guys set. There's there's
several variables going on there, but
kind of the kind of the common
denominator there is like how well you
can do it with the with the people lined
up with you. So you can kind of create
that synergistic type idea. So yeah,
it'll be interesting.
>> Hi Mike. Congratulations on a great
season.
>> Thanks.
>> Um, first of all,
>> ton of respect for the offseason you
guys had and and the work you did with
John. Seems like every every move that
you guys made worked out and it was a
lot of risk involved in it. Getting rid
of [snorts] DK, getting rid of of Gino,
bringing in a guy like Sam, and I think
it's not talked about enough how much
risk you guys took, but I'm sure you
guys never doubted the decision you guys
made, bringing in Clint to be the
offensive coordinator. Was there a point
in the season where you said like, "Heck
yeah, this is working out and the Super
Bowl is is is a real possibility now?"
>> Well, I listen to your question. I'm
thinking of
how the offseason felt in phase one,
two, and three. And what I felt was u a
great deal amount of enthusiasm, um
buyin that definitely hasn't been like
necessarily earned yet on from our part
as coaches. And that that was really
exciting. It's also a responsibility to
make sure that we're, you know, taking
advantage all those days and that they
that we do stack those days so you're
not just banging your head against the
wall every day. Um, and frankly, I mean,
look, our goal is to be here and win
this game, but you can't, and I've said
this earlier, but you can't you can't do
that unless you become a championship
team. So, our that was our goal from the
from the get-go of of how we have to
become the team that can win a game like
this. And, uh, that was really where our
focus was. And then and then that's
really that's where your focus is on
more of the process rather than thinking
okay like let's this is where we're
trying to get and uh and here we are.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you.